Guide to the Madeline Earle Stanton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Madeline Earle Stanton papers
1916-1983
MS 1482
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.75
(13 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, diaries, writings, memorabilia, and photographs documenting Madeline Stanton's bibliographic and administrative support of the work of Harvey Cushing and John Fulton, as well as her personal affairs.
Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Medical Historical Library, 1988; and gift of Ruth Judge, 1992 and 1994.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in four series: Series I. Correspondence, 1921-1983. Series II. Personal Papers, 1916-1981. Series III. Projects, 1922-1971. Series IV. Audiovisual Materials, 1927-1962.
Biographical / Historical
Madeline Earle Stanton was born on June 9, 1898, in Canton, Massachusetts. After receiving her B.A. degree from Smith College in 1919, she was secretary to Agide Jacchia, conductor of the Boston Pops Orchestra. Beginning in 1920, Stanton worked with Dr. Harvey Cushing at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital in Boston and later at the Yale School of Medicine. After Cushing's death in 1939, Stanton collaborated with Yale Professor John Fulton on bibliographic works on Michael Servetus and Robert Boyle. She was appointed secretary of the Yale Medical Historical Library in 1941. In 1949, her title changed to librarian of the Yale Medical Historical Collections. From 1951-1961, she was also research assistant in bibliography in the Yale Department of the History of Medicine. She was an assistant editor of the Journal of the History of Medicine and Allied Science from 1961-1972. Stanton died in Hamden, Connecticut on October 25, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, diaries, writings, memorabilia, and photographs documenting Madeline Stanton's bibliographic and administrative support of the work of Harvey Cushing and John Fulton, as well as her personal affairs.
Book collecting; Libraries; Medical libraries; Medicine -- History -- Study and teaching; Women; Diaries; Librarians; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Francis, William Willoughby, 1878-; Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960; Light, Richard Upjohn, 1902-1994; Schuman, Henry; Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle); Stevenson, Lloyd G., 1918-; Thomson, Elizabeth Harriet, 1907-; Yale Medical Library. Historical Library
- Correspondence, 1921-1983, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes Madeline Stanton's correspondence with her family, John Fulton, his family and students, and professional colleagues. The files are arranged alphabetically by personal and corporate name. The papers suggest the mixture of the professional with the personal in Stanton's life. The correspondence documents bibliographic and publication questions and administrative issues associated with the Yale Medical Historical Library.
  About twenty percent of the correspondence is from John Fulton. In his letters, Fulton describes many of the same conferences, trips, and other events which he recorded in his diaries. In treating Stanton as a confidante, Fulton expresses a more personal view of these events. The diaries, volumes of which are held in the Medical Historical Library, were widely shared with friends and relatives and, therefore, more circumspect.
  Other correspondents include Charles D. O'Malley, an authority on the work of Vesalius, associates from Harvey Cushing's group at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital including William R. Henderson, Hugh Cairns and Julia Shepley, and associates of John Fulton including Oliver Hayward and William W. Francis. Some correspondents, Francis for example, addressed letters to Stanton and Elizabeth Thomson jointly. The correspondence is closely associated with similar files in the papers of John Fulton (MS 1236) and Elizabeth Thomson (MS 1623). Business letters that Stanton wrote on behalf of Fulton are filed, for the most part, with the Fulton Papers.
  - A, 1933-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Association for the History of Medicine, 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
  - B, 1930-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bayne, Helen, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bell, Whitfield J., 1954-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
  - C, 1927-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cairns, Hugh, 1928-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Castiglioni, Arturo, 1944-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cushing, E. H., 1936-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cushing, Harvey, 1921-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cushing, Henry K., 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cushing, Kate, 1924-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Cutler, Elliott C., 1924-1931 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - D, 1927-1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - E, 1934-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - F, 1927-1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Francis, William W., 1942-1959 (Box 2, Folder 19 - 21)
  - Fulton, John F.
    General note
    See also: Series IV: Audiovisual Materials, Box 13, Folder 2
    - 1928 May-1929 February (Box 2, Folder 22 - 26)
    - 1929 March-1938 April (Box 3, Folder 27 - 41)
    - 1938 June-1952 August (Box 4, Folder 42 - 55)
    - 1953-1959 (Box 5, Folder 56 - 65)
  - Fulton, Lucia P. (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - 1930s and 1940s (Box 5, Folder 67 - 68)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - 1960s, undated (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Fulton family, 1941-1971 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - G-Gl, 1939-1978 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Go-Gu, 1930-1977 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Ha-He, 1931-1971 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Hi-Hu, 1935-1974 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Hayward, Oliver S., 1957-1964 (Box 6, Folder 76 - 78)
  - Henderson, William R., 1930-1940; 1969 (Box 6, Folder 79 - 80)
  - Horrax, Gilbert, 1933-1957 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Huston, K. Garth, 1954-1973 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - I, 1952-1965 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - J, 1921-1973 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - K, 1936-1979 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Keller, Deane, 1936-1972 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - L, 1934-1974 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - LeFanu, William R., 1948-1971 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Leibowitz, Jeannette and Joshua, 1957-1963 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Light, Richard Upjohn, 1932-1965 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Livingston, Robert
    See: Series IV: Audiovisual Materials, Box 13, Folder 3
  - Ma-Mc, 1931-1975 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Me-Mu, 1939-1975 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - MacLean, Paul D., 1956-1970 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Maddison, R. E. W., 1960-1964 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Meagher, Richard, 1931-1936 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Minnesota Historical Society, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Muirhead, Arnold, 1948-1966 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - N, 1947-1973 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - O, 1927-1973 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Oldberg, Eric, 1928-1977 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Oldberg, Hilda, 1931-1962 (Box 7, Folder 101 - 102)
  - O'Malley, Charles D., 1949-1968 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - P, 1939-1974 (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Poynter, F. Noel L., 1952-1966 (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Q, 1960-1963 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Ra-Re, 1939-1980 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Ri-Ru, 1928-1981 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Rankin, Leonard and Myra, 1927-1929 (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Rose, John Keith, 1954-1970 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Sa-Sj, 1938-1969 (Box 8, Folder 111)
  - Sm-Su, 1940-1975 (Box 8, Folder 112)
  - Schullian, Dorothy, 1947-1973 (Box 8, Folder 113)
  - Schuman, Henry and Ida, 1944-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - Shepley, Julia H.
    - 1921-1927 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - 1933-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 116 - 118)
  - Smith College, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - Soriano, Victor, 1961-1977 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Stevenson, Lloyd G., 1952-1975, undated (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - T, 1929-1975 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Thomas, Charles C., 1939-1951 (Box 9, Folder 123)
  - Thomson, Elizabeth, 1947-1962 (Box 9, Folder 124)
  - V, 1958-1961, n. d. (Box 9, Folder 125)
  - Wa-Wh, 1927-1971 (Box 9, Folder 126)
  - Wi-Y, 1937-1977 (Box 9, Folder 127)
  - Wagstaff, Donald [son of Donna and Joseph Wagstaff], 1974-1978 (Box 9, Folder 128)
  - Wagstaff, Dorothy [daughter of Donna and Joseph Wagstaff], 1975-1981 (Box 9, Folder 129)
  - Wagstaff, Heather [daughter of Donna and Joseph Wagstaff], 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 130)
  - Weed, Lewis H., 1949-1950 (Box 9, Folder 131)
  - Woodworth, Nancy R., 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 132)
  - Y-Z, 1940-1971 (Box 9, Folder 133)
  - Unidentified, 1923-1977, undated (Box 9, Folder 134)
- Personal Papers, 1916-1981; Series II
  This series is arranged by type of material. Of particular note are Stanton's handwritten diaries which contain personal reflections on family affairs and daily events in Cushing's unit at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital and at Yale University from 1928-1939. In them, she records her observations on colleagues, doctors, and cases. The diary typescripts from 1948 and 1951 describe her trips abroad. This series includes files on Madeline Stanton's estate, genealogy and memorabilia. Biographical information is available in a copy of a library school thesis on Madeline Stanton, which also includes a bibliography of her writings.
  - Biographical information
    - Diploma and memorabilia, 1920, 1929 (Box 14)
    - General, 1929-1981 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "M. E. Stanton and the Historical Library of the Yale Medical Library" [thesis by Joelle R. Blankfort], 1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Diaries
    - 1916, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1928 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1929 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1930 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1931 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1932-1933 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - [Europe], 1936 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - 1939 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - 1948 (Box 10, Folder 11)
      General
      Typescript.
    - 1951 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Estate [includes will; birth and death certificates], 1927, 1964-1965, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Genealogy, 1940, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Memorabilia, 1925-1973 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Notes [on music, literature, words], 1927-1928, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Projects, 1922-1971; Series III
  This series includes several files related to Stanton's writings about Cushing and the Yale Medical Historical Library. Additional files document projects relating to Stanton's association with Harvey Cushing. They include her notebook indexing Cushing's office files and her efforts to respond to requests for copies of the sculpture made of Cushing's hands. Correspondence concerning Stanton's work on the publication of the second edition of John Fulton's Selected Readings in the History of Physiology, particularly the illustrations used in the edition, is included.
  - Cushing, Harvey
    - Office files [notebook containing index]
      - 1922-1924 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - 1926-1934 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Hand, 1933-1969 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Correspondence re efforts to reproduce the original sculpture.
  - Selected Readings in the History of Physiology, 2nd ed. [illustrations, correspondence], 1963-1966 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Writings
    - Book reviews, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - "A Bouquet for Bill", 1956 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Harvey Cushing: Book Collector" [correspondence, draft], 1965 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "The Working Day of an Historical Library" [correspondence, draft], 1964 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "The Medical Historical Library on the Hundredth Birthday of Harvey Cushing", 1969 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1927-1962, undated; Series IV
  This series includes Soundscriber discs and photographs of Stanton. The Soundscriber discs include John Fulton's dictation responding to routine correspondence and Paul MacLean responding to Stanton's request for assistance in answering correspondence after Fulton's death. Of particular interest is the disc of Robert Livingston's discussion of Fulton's scientific work. This was made in response to Stanton's request for assistance in preparing an exhibition at the Yale Medical Library to honor Fulton after his death. Livingston had worked with Fulton in the Yale Laboratory of Physiology. Researchers must listen to the discs on equipment available in the Yale Historical Sound Recordings Room.
  - Photographs [Madeline Stanton, family, and friends], 1927-1962, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Soundscriber discs
    - Fulton, John F., 1940-1959 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Livingston, Robert B., MacLean, Paul, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 3)